All right בוקר
טוב. boker tov. Today’s דף daf is כ"ג, Kaf Gimmel, twenty-three. We
pick up at the bottom of כ"ב עמוד ב' Kaf Bet Amud
Bet and we are dealing, we're discussing the משנה Mishnah or related
issues to the משנה Mishnah about contradictory witnesses whether a woman's husband
died or whether a woman was divorced,
that she's not supposed to get married but if she's married she
doesn't have to leave, and then the ברייתא Braita where רב נחמן
Rav Nachman רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi is strict and he says that
actually she does have to leave unless the witnesses came after she
had already gotten married, the contradictory witnesses. Thank you. So now we
had an opinion in the גמרא Gemara which we actually just forgot
to read the last line of yesterday, רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan that
distinguished between contradictory witnesses about divorce and contradictory witnesses about death. That
in one case,
in the case of death she would not have to leave if
she had gotten married but in the case of divorce she would.
So the גמרא Gemara wanted to discuss the differences. We had a
couple of answers. The most recent one was that in the case
of divorce she would always be able to contradict the husband if
he showed up, so she’s not going to be as scrupulous to
check into it and therefore we cannot also add to this factor
the fact that she’s probably also sure about what happened. And now
the גמרא Gemara gives the last answer to that which we should
have read yesterday, one more sentence to end up the last סוגיא,
sugya, five lines from the bottom.
רב אסי Rav Asi אמר amar כגון דאמרי עדים עכשיו מת עכשיו
גירשה. kegon de'amri edim achshav met achshav gershah. So here’s the difference.
The witnesses didn't just decide to say she got divorced or that
the husband died like five years ago, they said yesterday. Yesterday we
saw the husband die. Yesterday we saw her get a divorce. And
then there are contradictory witnesses. So why in the case about death
can she if she gets married she can stay married but not
in the case of divorce? So it
says עכשיו מת עכשיו גירשה. achshav met achshav gershah. מיתה לא סלקא
לברורה. mita lo salka l'verurah. If they’re wrong about the death then
there is, I mean I forget if they're wrong, there’s no way
to bring additional evidence about the death. So there’s nothing that questions,
makes their testimony in question. I mean, yes, it’s contradictory testimony, but
there’s nothing additional that undermines it. So therefore בדיעבד bedieved if she
got married she could stay married.
Exactly. And presumably there’s no, it wouldn't, there wouldn't obviously be, maybe
there are, but it’s not like we can presume that there is
a problem here. Let’s just look at the contrast, okay? גירושין איכא
לברורה. gerushin ika l'verurah. But by the גט, get, you should say,
wait a minute, she got divorced yesterday, where’s the גט? get? Right?
You didn't lose the גט get since yesterday. And if you say
you lost it since yesterday, that already raises big question marks. So
therefore the basic principle is בדיעבד bedieved she could stay married if
there are these contradictory witnesses, but in the case where they say
she just got divorced yesterday, there’s something that additionally makes her position
suspect. Okay, that was the end of yesterday’s position. Let’s move on
to the next point. Oh, I’m sorry. דאמרינן לה de'amrinan lah we
say to her אי איתא דהכי הוה i ita dehachi hava if
you were just divorced yesterday אחוי לן
גיטך achvi lan gitach where's your גט? get? Okay. תנו רבנן. Tannu
Rabbanan. Okay, new topic. Not totally new, but whatever. תנו רבנן. Tannu
Rabbanan. שנים אומרים נתקדשה ושנים אומרים לא נתקדשה. shenayim omrim nitkadesha ushenayim
omrim lo nitkadesha. Two say she got married, two say she didn't
get married. הרי זו לא תינשא harei zu lo tinasei she can’t
marry another guy. Yeah, well presumably that doesn't matter, but presumably she’s
saying she didn't and that’s why she wants to marry this other
guy. ואם ניסת לא תצא ve'im nisset lo tetzei בדיעבד bedieved however
she can stay married to this other guy. Okay, so meaning again
the principle is where we're מחמיר, machmir, we’re afraid she is married,
but בדיעבד bedieved we allow her to stay
married to stay married to guy number two. שנים אומרים נתגרשה ושנים
אומרים לא נתגרשה. shenayim omrim nitgarshah ushenayim omrim lo nitgarshah. Two say
she got divorced and two say she didn't get divorce when we
knew she had been married from beforehand, okay? הרי זו לא תינשא
harei zu lo tinasei don’t marry to another person. Again לכתחילה l'chatachila
we’re מחמיר. machmir. ואם ניסת ve'im nisset if she did marry another
person תצא tetzei then she have to get divorced. We're not מיקל
meikel בדיעבד. bedieved. So what’s the difference? So the גמרא Gemara top
of כ"ג עמוד א' Kaf Gimmel Amud Aleph מאי שנא רישא ומאי
שנא סיפא? mai shna resha u-mai shna seifa? What’s the difference between
the first and last case? Now תוספות Tosafot points out what do
you mean, there’s a huge difference. Ever hear of the word חזקה?
chazakah? In the first case, she had a חזקה chazakah of being
a פנויה. penuyah. So therefore you had contradictory witnesses, בדיעבד bedieved she
got married we’ll assume that she remained that she was a פנויה
penuyah which is what she was before we even started listening to
the witnesses. Whereas in the other case, she started off being a
married woman. So בדיעבד bedieved she got married we’re going to go
back and assume she’s still a married woman and we’re going to
ask her to get and we’re going to force her to get
divorced. So תוספות Tosafot raises the question whatever the answer is it’s
worth, I mean, you know, the answer is not so clear, I
mean, you know, obvious in terms of it doesn’t solve it so
simply. But it’s worth pointing out that there is an obvious difference
here that in the case about yes, there are contradictory witnesses, let’s
ask about what her status was prior to the witnesses. The גמרא
Gemara for whatever reason doesn't give that answer and it wants to
know why by a פנויה penuyah in the case about whether she
had been married previously there’s contradictions we let her stay married to
this new guy, but not in the case about whether a woman
had been divorced. So let’s take a look. מאי שנא רישא ומאי
שנא סיפא? mai shna resha u-mai shna seifa? What’s the difference about
testimony whether she had been married, contradictory witnesses? contradictory testimony as opposed
to contradictory testimony about whether she had been divorced. So אמר אביי,
Amar Abaye, תרגמה בעד אחד. targuma b'eid echad. So this is going
to sound very familiar to answers we gave yesterday about differences between
death and a get, marriage and a get. So he says the
way you have to understand this is not contradictory pairs of witnesses,
but contradictory single witnesses. So let's play this out.
עד אחד אומר נתקדשה ועד אחד אומר לא נתקדשה. eid echad omer
nitkadsha v'eid echad omer lo nitkadsha. One witness says she got married,
one she says she didn't. תרווייהו בפנויה קמססהדי. travaihu b'pnuyah kamas'hadi. They're
both testifying that she started off as a פנויה. pnuyah. והאי דקאמר
נתקדשה, v'hai d'ka'amar nitkadsha, then you only have one witness that this
פנויה pnuyah got married. והאי דקאמר נתקדשה היי ליה אחד, v'hai d'ka'amar
nitkadsha hyei lei echad, it's only one, ואין דבריו של אחד במקום
שניים. v'ein devarav shel echad bimkom shnayim. He doesn't win out against
her her already affirmed status of being a פנויה. pnuyah. So therefore,
well it is, right, meaning it's in the end of the day
what אביי'ס Abaye's real argument does rest on is the fact about
what was her previous status. But rather than just saying the חזקה
chazakah is going to trump contradictory pairs of witnesses, for whatever reason
and that's what תוספות Tosafot says, maybe once you have contradictory witnesses
חזקה chazakah is no longer a
factor, is not right, not that it's no longer a factor, but
what it will trump is one witness that opposes it. So when
we shift it to one against one, then her previous status trumps
the one witness that's coming to change the status. So you're right,
effectively this is the חזקה chazakah argument, but winning out over one
witness.
Okay, what if there were two witnesses then in two
against two in
both cases we would say תיקו, teiku, exactly.
Okay, and the חזקה chazakah of the previous status would not be
relevant. Okay, now, עד אחד אומר נתגרשה ועד אחד אומר לא נתגרשה.
eid echad omer nitgarsha
v'eid echad omer lo nitgarsha. If one says she got divorced, one
says she didn't. תרווייהו באשת איש קמססהדי. travaihu b'eishet ish kamas'hadi. They're
both testifying that she had started off as a married woman, that
was her that was her established previous status. והאי דקאמר נתגרשה, v'hai
d'ka'amar nitgarsha, the one that says divorced, היי ליה אחד hyei lei
echad is only one witness against her חזקה, chazakah, ואין דבריו של
אחד במקום שניים, v'ein devarav shel echad bimkom shnayim, it doesn't win
out. So basically this is exactly the חזקה chazakah argument, but saying
that the חזקה chazakah will win against an עד אחד, eid echad,
it will not win against two even contradictory two witnesses. But once
it's two against two, that freezes everything in its tracks. So the
only way we can say here the previous status is relevant if
it's one against one. Yes Michael?
Where does and I know this comes into a play in other
places like קול, kol, like don't people know like there's
like a general...
Yeah, so you're exactly anticipating, excellent, you're exactly anticipating the next discussion.
So let's read the next answer. Okay, רב אשי
אמר לעולם תרי ותרי. Rav Ashi amar l'olam trei u-trei. No, it's
two and two, ואיפכא, v'ipcha, but reverse it. Actually the case is
that
שניים אומרים. shnayim omrim. Now, we'll see in a second, but basically
the point is that the case about the where it's a פנויה
pnuyah that's claimed to have gotten married, that's the case she does
have to leave her second marriage. Whereas if it's a married woman
who got divorced, she doesn't have to leave, which is a big
shocker. So let's see how he explains this. שניים אומרים ראינוה שנתקדשה.
shnayim omrim reinuha she-nitkadsha. Two say we saw her get
married. Okay, ושניים אומרים לא ראינוה שנתקדשה. u-shnayim omrim lo reinuha she-nitkadsha.
So now what he's doing is he's shifting it. Not only is
he reversing the ruling, but he's saying the other two are not
saying she didn't get married, we were there on that day you
claim she got married and she didn't get married. They're saying we
didn't see her get married, right? It's not like we saw that
she didn't, it's like we didn't see that she did.
That could be anybody in the world.
Exactly, exactly. So that's effectively the point. We're really going to wind
up just throwing out the second testimony. It's not relevant. So in
the first case, you have witnesses say she got married, that's the
one that's relevant, so she's assumed married, so she has to get
right, so she has to leave the second marriage. Whereas in the
other case, two says she got divorced, we throw out the two
that say they didn't see anything. Two says she got divorced, so
she's assumed to be divorced and she can stay in the second
marriage. Okay, so it sounds like not much of a חידוש. chidush.
So let's take a look at what he does with it.
שניים אומרים ראינוה שנתקדשה ושניים אומרים לא ראינוה שנתקדשה הרי זו לא
תינשא ואם ניסת תצא. shnayim omrim reinuha she-nitkadsha u-shnayim omrim lo reinuha
she-nitkadsha harei zo lo tinnasei v'im nisset tetzei. Don't get married and
if she does she has to get divorced. Because in the end
of the day we really only have one set of witnesses that
says she got married. פשיטא, Pshita, obviously. לא ראינוה אינה ראיה. lo
reinuha einah re'ayah. That the fact that we didn't see something, or
אינה ראיה, einah re'ayah, right, is actually it's לא ראיתי אינה ראיה.
lo raiti einah re'ayah. Not seeing something is not the same as
seeing the absence of something. Absence of evidence is not the evidence
of absence. Okay, so I didn't make that up. Okay,
that's I think that's a thing that they say in archaeology. Absence
of evidence is not evidence of absence. If you don't find certain
anyway
fine בדיוק אינה ראיה. b'diyuk einah re'ayah. Exactly, all right fine. Anyway,
okay. So לא ראינוה אינה ראיה. lo reinuha einah re'ayah. So anyway
what you didn't see isn't seeing or isn't a proof. So of
course the second testimony doesn't mean anything. All we have is witnesses
she got married. No, לא צריכא, lo tzricha, no, here's the case.
צריכא דדיירי בחצר אחת. Tzricha d'dayri b'chatzer achat. That they all lived
in the same courtyard. So מהו דתימא, mahu d'teima, so and two
said we were home the whole day and we never heard about
we never heard a wedding in the taking place in the courtyard.
Okay, so מהו דתימא, mahu d'teima, I might have thought
if if it was that she got married, קלא אית ליה למילתא
kala it lei lemilta there would have been some rumor, some discussion
that these people in the courtyard would have been saying, oh did
you hear חיים Chaim שרה Sarah got married? Oh really, wow. Was
חתן choson like blah blah blah? Anyway, we didn't hear any of
that stuff. So therefore, קא משמע לן kamashma lan that no, that
the lack of hearing anything or lack of seeing anything is not
relevant, דעבדי אינשי דמקדשי בצינעא d'avdi inshi d'mikadshi betzina it happens sometimes
people have a private quiet wedding and people don't... alright, that's going
to be the next part. That's going to be the next part.
Okay, so therefore, I might have thought that when they say we
didn't hear anything, that should be relevant, קא משמע לן kamashma lan
that it's not. By the way, it's relevant enough that we say
she's לכתחילה lechatchila not supposed to marry another guy. So it does
play a little bit of a weight. But בדיעבד bedi'eved we only
accept the testimony that she got... I'm sorry, no, that's not true,
this is where we're being מחמיר, machmir, where we're reviewing. Anyway, so
that's not relevant. So therefore,
even if she goes ahead and gets married, we force her to
get divorced because we only accept the testimony that she got married.
קא משמע לן kamashma lan that whatever דאיכא דמקדשי בצינעא. d'ika d'mikadshi
betzina. And now let's look at the next case: סיפא, seifa, the
final case. שנים אומרים ראינוה שנתגרשה ושנים אומרים לא ראינוה שנתגרשה הרי
זו לא תינשא. shnayim omrim reinuha shenitgarsha ushnayim omrim lo reinuha shenitgarsha
harei zo lo tinasei. So two say we didn't see her get
divorced, nevertheless they're not saying they saw that it didn't happen. So
לכתחילה lechatchila don't get married because you do have the two saying
that we didn't see the גט, get, but אם נישאת im niseis
בדיעבד bedi'eved if she did, לא תצא, lo teitzei, don't get divorced.
So don't leave the guy, because we really only have testimony that
there was a divorce. מאי קא משמע לן? mai kamashma lan? What's
the חידוש? chiddush? אע"ג דדיירי בחצר אחד af al gav d'dayri bechatzer
echad that even though they were in one courtyard we're not concerned
at the end of the day that witnesses say we didn't see,
we didn't hear about it. So היינו הך, hainu hach, that's what
we said before, that the fact that they didn't see something is
at the end of the day does not concern us even if
they're living in the same courtyard. No, it does because we say
לא תינשא lo tinasei though.
Oh, so right, so it obviously might concern us enough that we
say לא תינשא lo tinasei but certainly not enough
בדיעבד. bedi'eved. So מהו דתימא? mahu d'teima? I might have thought גבי
קידושין gabei kiddushin דעבדי אינשי דמקדשי בצינעא, d'avdi inshi d'mikadshi betzina, marriage
maybe happens, maybe sometimes there'll be a private wedding and therefore saying
we didn't hear about it in the end doesn't weigh in. אבל
גבי גירושין, aval gabei geirushin, but by the divorce, מי איכא דמיגרשא
קלא אית ליה למילתא? mi ika d'migarsha kala it lei lemilta? Everybody
loves talking about I don't know bad news or something, I don't
know, anyway maybe I would assume that everybody had heard about the
divorce, so there maybe the lack of hearing is weighty even בדיעבד,
bedi'eved, קא משמע לן kamashma lan דעבדי אינשי דמקדשי ומיגרשי בצינעא, d'avdi
inshi d'mikadshi umigarshi betzina, people both get married and divorced in private.
Okay, so that was a profound rereading of the case. He reversed
the פסק psak and he turned it into a case about not
we saw the opposite but we didn't hear that it did happen.
Anyway, so we have two potential distinctions. You have this debate of
רבי יוסי... Rabbi Yossi... who is it? רבי מנחם ברבי יוסי Rabbi
Menachem b'Rabbi Yossi that says even בדיעבד bedi'eved in all cases she
has to leave the second marriage unless the witnesses came after the
marriage, but if there were contradictory witnesses before, she has to leave
it. You have the חכמים Chachamim that say בדיעבד bedi'eved she can
stay. And then we have possible distinctions, distinctions between גירושין geirushin and
מיתה misa which might be built based on the issue of whether
she'd be afraid to lie or not, you know whether she'd be
afraid to be contradicted. And then a here difference between גירושין geirushin
and קידושין kiddushin where again I mean I'm dropping the, I'm focusing
on the two against two because there's other answers one against one,
reversing it, but assuming the two against two, the גמרא Gemara here
didn't really have a difference between the difference between גירושין geirushin and
קידושין. kiddushin. I mean תוספות Tosafot says the difference is חזקה, chazaka,
but in the end the גמרא Gemara only sort of accepted that
in a case of עד אחד ed echad not in the case
of two witnesses. Okay, so those were a whole series of contradictions
and
now we're going to go back to actually that case in our
משנה. mishna. And you might remember just to remind you that the
case in the משנה mishna is first set of contradictory witnesses about
whether a woman got a divorce and then a set of contradictory
witnesses about... I mean I'm sorry not contradictory, the גמרא Gemara has
been talking about contradictory, the משנה mishna is הפה שאסר hapeh she'asar
and but then הפה שאסר hapeh she'asar doesn't work if witnesses have
already established the first half of your statement. So the משנה mishna
had a הפה שאסר hapeh she'asar about a woman saying she was
divorced and then a הפה שאסר hapeh she'asar about a woman saying
that she was taken captive. All those cases she's believed, but then
the משנה mishna ends by saying but if there are witnesses that
established the first half of the statement then she is not believed
and even if she gets married she has to... I'm sorry
then she is not believed. However, if the witnesses came after she
got married then she can stay married. Yes Michael?
I'm just wondering if these rulings like oh they live in the
same courtyard and people perhaps the קידושין בצינעא kiddushin betzina and גירושין
בצינעא, geirushin betzina, what about אישות? ishus? Like they said, you know,
אישות ishus they say they're staying... what are you talking about, I've
been here this whole time.
All right, that's a good question but the נפקא מינה nafka mina
would be what? Like mostly for דיני ממונות dinei mamonus because it
wouldn't change her personal status for אישות, ishus, but that could be,
that could be. Okay, so again, the case of the משנה mishna
was, first she said, right, you know,
אשת איש, eishesh ish, you know, הייתי ונתגרשתי, hayisi venitgarashti,
what's the phrase there in the משנה? mishna? נתגרשתי. nitgarashti. אשת איש
הייתי. וגרושה אני. eshet ish hayiti vegrusha ani All right, well that
is easy, you do not have to worry about conjugating the verb.
Okay, וגרושה אני. vegrusha ani. Was it
וגרושה אני? vegrusha ani.
Okay, and then you had the other case about שבויה הייתי וטהורה
אני.
shvuya hayiti
uthora ani. Okay, so these are the two cases about פה שאסר.
peh she'asar. Okay, so then we say those are פה שאסר peh
she'asar and it is מותר. mutar. Okay, she is מותרת. muteret. Then
we had if there are עדים, edim, right? Let us use another
color.
If there are עדים edim that establish this, then she is אסורה,
asura, right? Because then she is not פה שאסר. peh she'asar. They
have established her אסור asur status. Okay, then that is stage two
of the משנה. mishnah. Then stage three says the משנה, mishnah, if
first she got married, right? She got married
and then came the witnesses, came the עדים, edim, then she is
מותרת, muteret, okay? Because in that case, right, she said this, she
got married, yeah, let us draw it like this. Okay, she said
this, she got married, right?
Because
she is מותרת. muteret. Then came along the witnesses that established the
first part, so then ואחר כך באו עדים, ve'acharkach bau edim, right?
ואחר כך
באו עדים, ve'acharkach bau edim,
so we say לא תצא, lo tetzei, okay? Since she already got
married בהיתר, beheter, even though when the witnesses come for this we
will not let her get married, but she got married בהיתר beheter
and then the witnesses came, then we say she could stay married,
okay? That is our משנה. mishnah. Let us take a look at
the גמרא. gemara. All right. באו עדים ואם משניסת באו עדים לא
תצא. bau edim ve'im misheniset bau edim lo tetzei. So says the
גמרא gemara the following. רבי אושעיא
מתני לה ארישא, Rabbi Oshaya matni la resha, רבה בר אבין מתני
לה אסיפא. Rabba bar Avin matni la seifa. Rabbi Oshaya teaches it
on the first part of the משנה mishnah and Rabbi Oshaya and
רבה בר אבין Rabba bar Avin teaches it on the second part.
מאן, man, so what does that mean? Meaning, is it going about
a case that she got married after saying אשת איש הייתי eishesh
ish hayisi. וגרושה אני vegrusha ani?
and then witnesses came and established that she had been married? Or
is it only about the case that she says she was a
שבויה וטהורה? shvuya uthora? And by the way, that is only really
relevant for a כהן. kohen. If she was raped as a שבויה,
shvuya, the only issue would be she could not marry a
כהן. kohen. So she said this and then she married a כהן
kohen and then witnesses came. So are witnesses challenging her status of,
you know, effectively challenging her status, not really contradicting her, but because
they are establishing the prior fact that winds up, you know, having
the effect of challenging her status. So are witnesses creating problems in
terms of her status of having prior been married or are they
creating a problem in terms of her status of possibly having been
raped? Okay, so in what, so that is the issue about whether
the, so she got married and then witnesses came. Do they come
on the first case or on the second case? Are they raising
the question of whether she is actually had been divorced or are
they implicitly raising the question about whether she had been raped? So
let us just read it, okay? רבי אושעיא מתני לה ארישא, Rabbi
Oshaya matni la resha, the witnesses came after the issue about having
been, the claim about having been married and divorced. So they are
basically now raising the question with her and her second husband whether
she actually had ever been, you know, raising the point that she
had been married before and raising the implicit question of whether she
had been divorced. רבה בר אבין מתני לה אסיפא. Rabba bar Avin
matni la seifa. And רבה בר אבין Rabba bar Avin says it
is the second case, where they are establishing she had been taken
as a captive, so they are implicitly raising the question with her
husband the כהן kohen whether or not she had been raped. So
מאן דמתני לה ארישא, man dematni la resha, if you say that
she can stay married even when the witnesses have established the fact
that she had previously been married raising the issue that she might
be, you know, that she might not have been divorced from the
first husband, so כל שכן סיפא. kol sheken seifa. Certainly, it will
be true that you will let her stay married in the second
case. דשבויה היא קילו. deshvuya hi kilu. The case about a woman
as captive that she is presumed to have been raped is rabbinically
she is presumed to have been raped. It is not biblical. So
therefore, if you are going to let her stay married in the
case where she might be, where the question is raised maybe she
is married to another man, that would be obviously a biblical issue,
you are certainly going to let her stay married when the only
question is maybe she had been raped, that she had been a
שבויה, shvuya, okay, which is only a, I mean raped is the
biblical concern, but being a שבויה shvuya not knowing she is raped
is only a rabbinic concern. ומאן דמתני לה אסיפא, uman dematni la
seifa, but if you say we let her stay married in the
case where the witnesses established that she had been taken captive, אבל
ארישא לא, aval aresha lo, but we would not let her stay
married if the witnesses had established that she had been married to
another man. That raises the real question that maybe she is committing
adultery, okay? So therefore, even if בדיעבד bediavad she got married, we
would not let her stay married because now we do not know
that she, we have not established, you know, with sufficient testimony, with
sufficient weight that she had been divorced. So you get it? She
went ahead at this stage, she was totally okay to marry, but
now witnesses say, one minute, you had been married before. So now
we know she had been married before, we do not have testimony
that she had been divorced. It is very nice she is married
to another man, but we have not established that she has been
divorced and we know she has been married. So maybe we will
not allow that even though we have רחמנות rachmanus that she is
now married to another guy. Maybe we cannot tolerate that case. Okay,
so now the גמרא gemara wants to understand, okay, that is a
very good point. If it's only the rabbinic issue that she was
captive, we don't know what happened, we can understand that we can
let things continue once she's already remarried to another guy. But if
it is the biblical issue, we've established now that she had been
married to another man, there's no testimony of divorce, how could we
tolerate her to continue to stay married? So now the גמרא Gemara
is going to spell it out. Let's take a look. לימא דרב
המנונא קמיפלגי. leima d'Rav Hamnuna kamipalgi.
Let's say they're debating רב המנונא. Rav Hamnuna. דמאן דמתני לה ארישא,
d'man d'matni la reisha, if you say that we'll let her stay
married even when it's been established they've been previously married, אית ליה
דרב המנונא. it lei d'Rav Hamnuna. He owes רב המנונא. Rav Hamnuna.
What's רב המנונא? Rav Hamnuna? רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna is the one
who said, we quoted yesterday, that a woman who says to her
husband, I was, you divorced me, is believed. חזקה אין אשה מעיזה
פניה בפני בעלה. chazaka ein isha me'iza paneha bifnei ba'ala. A woman
would not be so brazen to claim that against her husband. So
the reason we're going to let her stay married in this case
is that even when witnesses come and establish they've been previously married,
she's obviously claiming that she's divorced, right? She's not saying she doesn't
know, she's obviously claiming she's divorced. So that allows us to let
her stay married.
Is this the בעל ba'al case?
What? Yeah, we have to assume, well that's what we're assuming, that
the husband is around and she's saying it to his face.
But if not, then she wouldn't.
Okay, so that, you're right. The גמרא Gemara says you raise a
good question. How could we let her stay married if there's no
evidence she was divorced and if witnesses have established it, that she
had been married? So that's fine, the way she stays married is
because her claim into her husband's face is given the weight of,
is given the similar weight as that of witnesses. Okay. דמאן דמתני
לה אסיפא לית ליה דרב המנונא. d'man d'matni la seifa leit lei
d'Rav Hamnuna.
But if you say no, then you don't agree with רב המנונא,
Rav Hamnuna, that even if she says it to the husband's face,
it's not weight, it doesn't, it's not believed. גמרא Gemara says לא.
lo. No, we don't have to say they debate רב המנונא. Rav
Hamnuna. דכולי עלמא אית להו דרב המנונא. d'chulei alma it lehu d'Rav
Hamnuna. Everybody can agree with רב המנונא. Rav Hamnuna. והכא בהא קמיפלגי.
ve'hacha behai kamipalgi. Here's the debate. מר סבר כי אמרה רב המנונא
בפניו. mar savar ki amrah Rav Hamnuna befanav.
So you see, Michael, you totally anticipated the גמרא. Gemara. אבל שלא
בפניו מעיזה. aval shelo befanav me'iza.
Who says the husband's around? The husband isn't around. So if she
was saying it to the husband's face, everybody would agree she could
stay married. But she's not saying it to the husband's face. She's
saying it, but the husband isn't physically present. So one says, okay,
so she's willing to be brazen and lie, and therefore we've established
she's been previously married. I'm sorry, you gotta get divorced from this
second guy. ומר סבר, u'mar savar, the other says, שלא בפניו נמי
אינה מעיזה. shelo befanav nami eina me'iza. No, even not in his
presence, she would not so brazenly lie because obviously he could always
show up and contradict her. Okay, so actually, so you know, again,
in יבמות Yevamos we learned a lot of cases where we had
where the רבנים rabbanim really went out on a limb to bend
certain rules of evidence in order to not like, you know, make
the woman עגונה aguna and so on. So this is another case
where it's actually interesting. She went out and she got married, it
was totally okay at the time, but now we've actually proven that
she had been previously married and we have no proof of a
גט, get, and we're still going to let her stay married. And
the reason is because we're going to add to it the fact
that she's making the claim that she's divorced. And even though it's
not in the presence of a husband, that'll be enough for us
to let her stay married. Yes.
Isn't there an issue here in terms of protocol to make this
even more pointed? In other words, the husband's not around, but how
about בפני בית דין? bifnei beis din? The assumption is she wouldn't
brazenly...
No, because you don't lie in front of somebody who knows you're
lying, right? I mean, then we would say that everybody's always believed
in every claim they say in court because people don't lie in
front of a בית דין. beis din. You know, the whole חידוש
chiddush here is, is that A, and I think it obviously assumes,
number one, a whole sort of, you know, norms that exist with,
like, you know, within a patriarchy about women and their relationship to,
to, to their husbands, okay. But also and it's also somebody who
knows that you're lying. We had also a principle about אין אדם
מעיז פניו בפני בעל חובו, ein adam me'iz panav bifnei ba'al chovo,
right?
So you obviously lie to other people, but the question is, do
you lie to the person who knows you're lying and the person
to whom you owe a debt? So that's the case of בעל
חובו. ba'al chovo. The guy was so nice, he lent you money,
and now you're going to turn around and lie to him? So
that, it's not just a point that you don't lie in, you
don't lie to people who know you're lying, but you don't lie
to people who you have a certain type of a relationship to.
Maybe, you know, an indebted relationship to or a husband and wife
and her... power relationship to, right. So exactly, yes. Does בפני בעלה
bifnei ba'ala mean literally in front of
husband, or does it mean like, you know, in his community, like
in front of...
No,
no, we assume it means in front of, yeah.
Confronting him right there. Yeah. Okay. And fine.
ואם משנישאת באו עדים.
v'im mishe'nisess
ba'u eidim.
Now, go, still back on this. She got married, witnesses come, she
can stay married, and we've just discussed whether it means in which
of the two cases are we talking about. אמר אבוה דשמואל, Amar
Avuha d'Shmuel, said the father of שמואל, Shmuel, לא נישאת נישאת ממש,
lo nisess nisess mamash, אלא, ela,
now
again, it's interesting to see, right, how, how we keep on sort
of expanding this and letting her, you know, being, not forcing her
to get divorced. So it's a, and not only not forcing her
to get divorced, as we're gonna see, being, you know, lenient about
her status. So this idea that once witnesses come she's stuck, I
mean, once witnesses come she can stay married, as long as she's
already got married, he says you don't even have to have gotten
married. לא נישאת נישאת ממש, lo nisess nisess mamash, אלא כיון שהתירוה
לינשא. ela keivan she'tirua l'inases. Once she said the פה שאסר, peh
she'assar, and בית דין beis din ruled that she could get married,
אף על פי שלא נישאת, af al pi she'lo nisess, even if
she hasn't yet gotten married, then she, she can go ahead and
she, she's totally fine once she got that ruling from בית דין.
beis din. And again, this is even a bigger חידוש chiddush because
again, remember this would be a case even if she goes ahead
and she says, like, if a woman's really smart, right, what she
does is she runs to בית דין, Beis Din, right? It's all
about the question about like who gets, you know, who gets to
court first, right? So she comes to a new town and she
runs to בית דין Beis Din and she says, "I was married
and I got divorced. Can I go ahead and get married?" So
they say, "Oh, okay, הפה שאסר, ha-peh she-asar, go get married." And
then, two days later, we find we have evidence that she was
married and we have no evidence of a גט. get. So according
to אבוה דשמואל, Avuha d'Shmuel, oh wait, I already got a פסק,
psak, I can go ahead and get married. Okay? You don't it's
not even that if we would have to force a divorce do
we let her, but once she got the פסק, psak, we let
her keep the פסק. psak. Okay, now that's a huge חידוש chiddush
again, especially in the case where she might be an אשת איש.
eishet ish. She might be a married woman, we have evidence she
was a married woman, we have no evidence of a גט, get,
and according to אבוה דשמואל, Avuha d'Shmuel, once she got the פסק,
psak, she's entitled to keep it. Presumably backed up by this idea
of איני זמה ואיזו פניה. eini zama v'eizu paneha. But still, it's
pretty amazing. Just run to בית דין, Beis Din, do your הפה
שאסר, ha-peh she-asar, get them to פסקן pasken on your הפה שאסר
ha-peh she-asar before they get in any other information and then you've
got a lock on that פסק. psak. Yes.
So once you've got the פסק, psak, yes, seems like it could
be a general principle that could be abused in a lot of
other— Well, that's my point. I mean, that that's it's pretty surprising.
Doesn't sound like that though.
I agree, that's which is what the גמרא's Gemara going to ask.
So the גמרא... Gemara...
very... parallel, I mean, from my understanding is in Israel it depends
who whoever initiates proceedings gets to choose the venue.
Right, yeah, that's what I was alluding to. In Israel that's a
big deal, but that's because about whether you have a גט get
vs. whether you do divorce in a בית דין Beis Din or
in a בית משפט, Beis Mishpat, whether in the secular court or
the one or the religious court. And the question is whoever basically
files first. So also raises whole issues because it doesn't give a
couple time to work things out because there's a whole race for
the venue.
Anyway, but otherwise she can't keep her גט get forever, right? Because
it can always be challenged at some point?
Yeah, well, she can get it registered in the court, but basically,
and
the court gets records, hopefully. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
Okay, והלא, ve-halo, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. והלא לא
תצא קתני. ve-halo lo teitzei katani. But it says she doesn't have
to get divorced. It doesn't say that she's allowed to still get
married. No, לא תצא מהיתר הראשון lo teitzei me-heter ha-rishon means that
she doesn't have to abandon her first, you know, the פסק, psak,
the היתר heter that she got, the permission that she got. Yeah,
it's a very big stretch of the משנה. Mishna. You might remember
we had a we had this similar line existed in in מסכת
יבמות Masechet Yevamot where we re-read an idea about about like it
didn't even have to get married yet, you just got the פסק
psak and then you got the lock-in. Okay, so that's a big
חידוש. chiddush. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. אמר נשביתי וטהורה אני. amar nishbeiti
u-tehorah ani. So this is the case of the משנה. Mishna. She
says I was taken captive but I am pure, I was not
raped. ויש לי עדים שטהורה אני, ve-yesh li eidim she-tehorah ani, and
not only that, there were witnesses with me that saw that I
was that I wasn't abused. So אין אומרים נמתין עד שיבואו עדים.
ein omrim namtin ad she-yavo'u eidim. So this is interesting. We might
say look, she's telling us that there are witnesses, we might as
well wait in order to, you know, more firmly establish it. No,
we don't say that. It's a הפה שאסר ha-peh she-asar case. There's
no witnesses that said that she was captive. So we might as
well give the פסק psak now.
So אלא מתירים אותה מיד, ela matirin osah miyad, we permit her
immediately. התירוה להינשא, hitiruha l'hinasei, now we permitted her, ואחר כך באו
עדים, ve-achar kach ba'u eidim, and then the witnesses came. And the
witnesses came, they did two things. Number one is they established that
she had been captive, so that's going to undermine the הפה שאסר.
ha-peh she-asar. And how about the fact that she said the witnesses
would testify to the fact that she had not been raped? So
what did they actually say? ואמרו לא ידענו. ve-amru lo yadanu. We
said, "Ah, we don't know." I mean, sure we saw most of
the time she was being treated nicely, but we weren't watching the
whole time. We can't testify to the fact that she wasn't raped.
Okay, so effectively what the witnesses are now saying is we know
she was taken captive. So does that go ahead and undermine the
הפה שאסר? ha-peh she-asar? So let's take a look. לא ידענו הרי
זו לא תצא. lo yadanu harei zo lo teitzei. No, she already
got her permission, so this is what we
said, she doesn't have to get divorced once she acted on the
פסק psak of בית דין. Beis Din. According to אבוה דשמואל, Avuha
d'Shmuel, it would even be even before she acted on the פסק.
psak. She got the פסק psak of בית דין. Beis Din. Since
she got the פסק, psak, even now that witnesses establish she was
captive, she's entitled to keep her היתר. heter. Okay, הרי זו לא
תצא. harei zo lo teitzei. ואם באו עדי טומאה, ve-im ba'u edei
tumah, but if witnesses come and say no, actually we saw her
get raped, אפילו יש לה כמה בנים, afilu yesh lah kama banim,
now again this is all as that she's married to a כהן,
kohen, even if she has many children, so תצא, teitzei, she has
to get divorced. Now כמה בנים, kama banim, sometimes the נפקא מינה
nafka mina would be and then you're implicitly saying the kids are
ממזרים. mamzerim. That wouldn't be the case here. Here the case would
be you'd be saying the kids are חללים chalalim if they were
born after the fact. Okay, but anyway, nevertheless, if there's clear witnesses,
there's going to be no רחמנות rachmanut if we actually know, you
know, have hard evidence to that fact. Okay, so not a lot
of big חידושים chiddushim now based on what we had said before.
The biggest חידוש chiddush was the first point that we don't wait
for more witnesses, we just are willing to פסקן. pasken. And once
you add אבוה דשמואל, Avuha d'Shmuel, once we gave her the פסק,
psak, she keeps the היתר heter even if witnesses come afterwards, but
of course witnesses of the actual rape, that's different. Okay, תא שמע.
ta shema.
Now, a story. הני שבוייתא דאתיין לנהרדעא. hani shevuyata d'atyan l'Neharde'a. There
were some female captives that were taken to נהרדעא. Neharde'a.
And they basically were in the process about being redeemed, okay, from
their captors.
But
yeah or yeah you ransom it back. I mean this might here
this case about שבויים shvuyim being פודים podem might be a little
bit more like the standard kidnapping we think about because it might
be that you're redeeming them back to their community or to their
parents. Anyway so that's the cases that we're talking about, okay? And
we'll see actually גמראס gemaras talk about whether maybe sometimes captors דווקא
davka don't rape the victims in order so that because you know
they're just in it for the money. So okay so anyway let's
take a look. So there were these captives, female captives that came
to נהרדעא Nahardea and they were being sort of their release was
being negotiated or something and they were being redeemed and אותיב אבוה
דשמואל נטורי בהדייהו. Otiv avuha dishmuel natore behadihu.
So the father of שמואל, Shmuel, right, and he had that פסק
psak before about התירא הראשון hetera harishon you might remember anyway so
he went ahead and he basically appointed somebody to watch them, you
know, to watch them until the whole thing had been resolved so
that they made sure they didn't get raped or exactly. Maybe now
that they're in the town, maybe people feel that they can
take advantage of these female captives. So he appointed somebody to watch
over them. אמר ליה שמואל, Amar lei Shmuel, so שמואל Shmuel said
to them, ועד האידנא מאן נטרינהו, ve'ad idna man natrinhu, so who
was watching them until now? I mean you know they were in
the hands of the captors and so on so you know like
now you could read that לקולא או לחומרא. lekula o lechumra. You
could read that לקולא lekula which is basically saying we don't need
to watch them because we're going to assume that you know anyway
it's going to be a פסק psak or whatever it's going to
be we're going to assume they weren't raped. תוספות Tosafot says that
שמואל Shmuel actually meant it לחומרא lechumra that he's basically was saying
like what good does it do? We got to assume they were
raped anyway, they weren't watched until now so what good is it
going to do now to have captives. So of course the question
is not just can they marry כהנים kohanim maybe he just cared
about their welfare, you know what I mean? Like it's one question
about what happened in the past and whether they can marry a
כהן kohen it's another question of are people going to take advantage
of them. Anyway so that's what שמואל Shmuel said and who was
watching them until now.
So he said back to him אמר ליה amar lei so his
father said back to him אילו בנתייך הוין ilu bnatayikh havyon if
these were your daughters מי הוות מזלזל בכולהי האי mi havat mezalzel
bekulhai hai you would not be so you would not mistreat them
so much, which might be just saying like forget about what happened
in the past, you know? We got to take care of them
right now. They're here in נהרדעא Nahardea we have to protect them
we have to you know we have to we have to come
and take care and they're our responsibility. Okay. So he says, so
he says if they were your daughters you would not be so
you know disparaging. הוה כשגגה שיוצא מלפני השליט Hava keshigaga sheyotse milifnei
hashalit it was like a error that went out from the presence
of the ruler meaning you know a slip of the tongue and
you know when rabbis say important things and they slip their tongue
so that maybe it's a type of an אל תפתח פה לשטן
al tiftach pe lasatan type of an idea. ואשתביין בנתיה דמר שמואל
Ve'ishtabiyan bnatia demar Shmuel and what happened soon afterwards? שמואל'ס Shmuel's daughters
were taken captives because his father said if they were your daughters
you wouldn't have said this. His daughters and granddaughters too. I understand
he didn't want it to happen but once he was פותח פה
לשטן poteach pe lasatan that's what happened okay.
I
know alright exactly anyway so okay now what happened so now we
have to have the end of that story ואסקינהו לארעא דישראל ve'askinhu
le'ar'a deyisrael so these his daughters were taken to ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. שמואל'ס Shmuel's daughters yes. Sort of now now it's like a
יוסף Yosef and the המדיינים hamidyanim story, okay. His daughters were taken
to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael that's where the captors took them. ואוקמינהו
לשבויינהו מאבראי Ve'ukminhu lishvuyinhu me'avarai
so then they were being brought to a certain Jewish town and
the captors were going to try to ransom them off and they
so they said to their captors I'm going to tell you so
they said to their captors they were brought to a town and
like they were going to go into apparently a בית מדרש beit
midrash or something to raise them funds for to to you know
to ransom them off. So they said to their captors guys stay
outside here let us go and talk to the rabbis inside the
בית מדרש beit midrash this is what שמואל'ס Shmuel's daughters said to
them okay so they made the captors sit outside ועיילו לבי מדרשא
דרבי חנינא ve'ayilu levei midrashya derabbi Chanina
they went into the בית מדרש beit midrash of רבי חנינא. Rabbi
Chanina. הא אמרה Ha amra
so one of the women said of שמואל'ס Shmuel's daughters נשביתי וטהורה
אני nishbeiti uthora ani
guys I was taken captive but I am still I have not
been raped and the captors are outside and you know go ahead
and ransom me off and then maybe one of you guys wants
to marry me okay so you know בית מדרש beit midrash full
of full of men. Okay so anyway נשביתי וטהורה אני nishbeiti uthora
ani the other one
said נשביתי וטהורה אני nishbeiti uthora ani so שרינהו shareinhu so they
basically they were learned exactly so they פסקנד paskened oh okay you're
מותר mutar and now let's go and redeem you okay so סוף
ואתו שבויינהו sof ve'atu shvuyinhu
in the end the captors came in.
אמר רבי חנינא Amar Rabbi Chanina so רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina said
who was the one that פסקנד paskened that okay בנתיה דמר שמואל.
bnatia demar Shmuel. בנן דמרן אינון, Bnan demoran inun,
they are the daughters of a great man, of a great rabbi,
okay? Because they were smart enough to know first come and make
your claim, do your פה שאסר peh she-asar before you introduce problematic
information, okay? And remember, it was Shmuel's father, their grandfather, that said
that once they got the פסק, psak, it wouldn't have to be
retracted. Now, of course, okay, when the captors themselves are there, they're
not necessarily, I'm assuming they're not Jewish, but anyway, so it's not
like there's testimony, but there is evidence, right? There's not going to
be testimony that they were taken captive, but there's actually going to
be, like, in the face of them, their captors are going to
actually be, you know, presently taking control over them, so that presumably
would be as bad or, you know, as actual testimony that they've
been taken captive. So before establishing that fact to everybody's eyes that
they had been taken captive, they got their פסק, psak, it was
a פה שאסר, peh she-asar, then the captors walked in the door.
Oh, you already got your היתר, heter, we're not going to retract
the היתר. heter. One minute, okay? So you must have been children
of a real תלמיד חכם talmid chacham that you knew how to
handle this case. איגלאי מילתא דבנתיה דמר שמואל הוו, Iglai milta debnateh
demar Shmuel havu, lo and behold, it turned out they were the
daughters of Mar Shmuel. And thankfully, because their grandfather had פסקנד paskened
that the פסק psak doesn't get reversed, so now actually they could,
you know, even before they were married, they could go ahead and
operate on the first פסק. psak. אמר ליה רבי חנינא לרבי שמן
בר אבא, Amar leih Rabbi Chanina leRabbi Sheman bar Abba, so Rabbi
Chanina, who again, he was the, it was his בית מדרש, beit
midrash, he said to Rabbi Sheman bar Abba, פוק איטפל בקרובותייך, Puk
itapel bikrovotaich,
go take care of your relatives. Apparently, he was somehow related to
them, and he, it was basically a way of saying, like, you
know, you should marry them. Okay, he wasn't so related that he
couldn't marry them. Okay? So אמר ליה Amar leih to Rabbi Chanina,
he didn't marry one of
them, והאיכא, Ve-ika, right,
that's true.
והאיכא, Ve-ika, so anyway, maybe help them get married or something. והאיכא
עדי במדינת הים, Ve-ika edi bimdinat hayam,
aren't there witnesses overseas? Which is funny, like, who needs the witnesses
overseas, you actually saw the captors in your face. Again, so it's
an interesting question about, do people who are right now walking around
acting as captors, does that establish the fact they were taken, I
don't know, you know, it's a little bit unclear what the presence
of the captors is doing. Anyway, so he said, aren't there those
witnesses? השתא מיהת ליתנהו קמן, Hashta mihat leitnehu kaman, the Gemara says,
השתא מיהת ליתנהו קמן. Hashta mihat leitnehu kaman. Okay,
but right now we're not dealing with the witnesses, they're not in
front of us. עדי בצד אסתן ותיאסר? Edi betzad astan veteaser?
Witnesses are somewhere on the other side of the ocean, you know,
Astan's like some distant city, and now you're going to say it's
forbidden? We can't worry about distant witnesses. Right now they're מותר mutar
and we're going to act on them. So now the Gemara says,
one minute, who cares if there were witnesses? טעמא דלא אתו עדי,
Taama dela atu edi, the only reason that it was okay was
because witnesses hadn't arrived. הא אתו עדי, Ha atu edi, if witnesses
had come, מיתסרא, mitsara, it's implying that they would be forbidden. ואמר
אבוה דשמואל, Ve-amar avuh deShmuel, but again, their grandfather, the father of
Shmuel said, כיון שהתירוה שוב לא תיאסר, Keivan she-hitiruha shuv lo te-aser,
that once they got their היתר, heter, their היתר heter isn't going
to get lost. And again, that was pretty evident because then the
captors walked in the door, and they remained with their היתר. heter.
So who cares about witnesses? אמר רב אשי עדי טומאה איתמר. Amar
Rav Ashi edi tumah itmar.
No,
there was a concern that there were witnesses that they had been
raped, not just witnesses that they had been captive. So he says,
one minute, I can't go ahead and marry them. Apparently he was
a כהן. kohen. How could I marry them? You know, it's very
nice you have a פה שאסר peh she-asar and the whole thing,
but I heard that there were witnesses that they had been raped.
So we don't have to worry about that. Of course, the sad
thing is, very nice that we don't have to worry about that,
he's going to marry them, and then he might be completely הלכתית,
halachically, you know, okay now, but ten years later, the witnesses will
show up and we said אפילו כמה בנים תצא. afilu kama banim
tetze. So it's one thing to say, like, הלכתית halachically you're allowed
to marry them now, and you don't have to say I shouldn't
be allowed because maybe there are witnesses. But just in terms of,
like, you know, just in terms of consequences, of right thinking about
the future, you might not want to marry somebody who ten years
from now, you know, you're going to have to divorce because the
witnesses are going to show up. So anyway, the Gemara doesn't deal
with that, but that's anyway the end of this idea about אבוה
דשמואל Avuh deShmuel and the point about even
in the case of שבויה shvuya which is דרבנן, drabbanan, but possibly
even the case of אשת איש, eshet ish, once the witnesses show
up, you don't have to get divorced, and not only do you
not have to get divorced, but you don't even lose your original
היתר, heter, unless there're witnesses that the event actually occurred, unless there're
witnesses that they actually, you know, were
raped. That would make a difference. Yes, there were a couple of
questions, though, yes.
I just don't remember, is there any difference לגבי כהן legabei kohen
if the rape was by a Jew or a non-Jew?
No, the difference is that if it's a
consensual
sex with a non-Jew even before marriage makes the woman forbidden to
a כהן, kohen, whereas once the woman is married,
then, I mean like consensual, doesn't matter consensual, non-consensual from a Kohen's
perspective, sex with a non-Jew will always make a woman forbidden to
a כהן kohen even if it occurred outside of marriage, whereas once
the woman is married,
sex even non-consensual sex will make her forbidden regardless of Jew or
non-Jew. Okay? Which is anyway, that's the big issue is nowadays, you
know, if somebody wants to marry a כהן kohen who's
particularly
a בעל תשובה baal teshuvah or whatever, just hasn't been, you know,
has been sexually active and
slept with a
non-Jew, so.
Is this סוגיא sugya ever cited in the debates over teaching Torah
to women?
Ha ha ha. Oh, you mean because למדה תפלות? limdah tiflut? Because
now she knows... I don't think תפלות tiflut is dealing with the
fact that she might have been raped. But, but it's an interesting
point, you know, and it does sort of show you that since,
it's a good, it's a good point because you know, the whole
concern about the גמרא Gemara about the one opinion in the משנה:
Mishnah: כל המלמד את בתו תורה כאילו מלמדה תפלות kol hamelamed et
bito torah ke'ilu melamdah tiflut is that, you know, is that if
you know how to like manipulate the system sometimes, and that was
in the context of סוטה Sotah and concerns about, you know, women
and and the and the men's concern about women acting sexually improperly,
you know, which, you know, and so on. So it does somewhat,
it does somewhat relate to those issues. Okay.
Turning the page, עמוד ב. Amud Bet.
שתי נשים. Shte nashim. What time... Oh my god, it's already 8:17,
how did it get so late? שתי נשים Shte nashim שנשבו. shenishbu.
Yes, exactly. Two women are taken captive. זו אומרת נשביתי וטהורה אני.
Zo omeret nishbeti utehorah ani. Now again, the presumption is going to
be here that there are witnesses that they were taken captive, because
שנשבו shenishbu presumably means we know they were taken captive. זו אומרת
נשביתי וטהורה אני. Zo omeret nishbeti utehorah ani. This one says: I
was captive and I'm טהורה. tehorah. וזו אומרת נשביתי וטהורה אני. Vezo
omeret nishbeti utehorah ani. Yes, I'm טהורה. tehorah. אינן נאמנות. Einan ne'emanot.
They are not believed, because presumably there are witnesses that they were
taken captive, so you're not believed to say you weren't raped. However,
בזמן שהן מעידות זו את זו. Bizman shehen me'idot zo et zo.
If they testify about one another, הרי אלו נאמנות. Harei elu ne'emanot.
They are believed, because since again the whole idea about שבויה shvuyah
is a דרבנן, d'rabbanan, because we don't know that they were raped,
and remember again this is all about a כהן. kohen. So the
רבנן rabbanan were willing to believe even עדת אשה edut ishah as
long as you're not testifying about yourself. As long as you're testifying
about someone else, you are going to be, even a woman is
believed, and even one witness is believed to say that the that
another woman was not raped in a case of a taken captive.
Which should also point out that part of the חידוש chiddush here
is not just that we're believing women who normally don't count as
witnesses, we're believing one witness, but even it's even a case which
the גמרא Gemara is going to refer to as גומלין, gomlin, which
is a possible concern of reciprocity, right? Again, if you know the
הלכה, halakhah, it's like, hey, okay, if we talk about ourselves, they're
not going to believe us. I'll testify about you and you testify
about me, right? Very reasonable that people would make that deal, and
nevertheless we are willing to believe them. Okay, so let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan.
אני טמאה וחברתי טהורה. Ani tme'ah vechaverti tehorah. If a woman says,
I am טמאה tme'ah and my friend is טהורה. tehorah. נאמנת. Ne'emanet.
She's believed. That's fine, right? She's not testifying about herself, I mean,
only detrimentally, and her testimony about her friend is believed. אני טהורה
וחברתי טמאה. Ani tehorah vechaverti tme'ah. I am טהורה, tehorah, I was
not raped, but my friend was. אינה נאמנת. Einah ne'emanet. She's not
believed about herself, for because as we said, and, she's not believed
to make her friend's situation any worse, meaning there might be a
presumption that her friend has been raped, but her testimony doesn't like,
you know, give it any additional weight.
But they say, maybe they
say she
got married... let's not worry about צא צא Tze Tze yet. So
anyway... אני וחברתי טמאה. Ani vechaverti tme'ah. I and my friend are
both
טמאה. tme'ah. נאמנת... Ne'emanet... What? נאמנת על עצמה. Ne'emanet al atzmah. Thank
you. ואינה נאמנת
על חברתה.
Ve'einah
ne'emanet al chavertah.
She's believed about herself, because you want to say you're טמאה, tme'ah,
גזונטערהייט. gezunterheit. But she's not believed about her friend. Again, you can't
testify about somebody else that she was that she was raped. I
certainly one witness and so on. אני וחברתי טהורה. Ani vechaverti tehorah.
I and my friend are טהורה. tehorah. נאמנת על חברתה ואינה נאמנת
על עצמה. Ne'emanet al chavertah ve'einah ne'emanet al atzmah.
She's believed about her friend, because of what we've already learned, that
you're believed to say somebody else wasn't raped, but not about yourself.
So all that seems pretty straightforward. The גמרא Gemara is going to
complicate it though. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר
מר. Amar mar. אני טהורה וחברתי טמאה. Ani tehorah vechaverti tme'ah. I
am טהורה tehorah and my friend is טמאה. tme'ah. אינה נאמנת. Einah
ne'emanet. She's not believed, neither about her friend, herself, or about her
friend. היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's the case? אי דליכא עדים. Ei
delika edim. If there are no witnesses,
why isn't she believed about herself? Right? She's just saying, נשביתי וטהורה
אני. nishbeti utehorah ani.
So that's the classic case where she's saying she's taken captive and
she's טהורה, tehorah, הפה שאסר. ha'peh she'asar. אלא פשיטא. Ela pshita. It
must be דאיכא עדים. de'ika edim. Right? That's presumably the case of
everything here, that there are already witnesses, and that's why it's all
problematic.
Okay, so there's already witnesses, she's not believed to say that she's
טהורה. tehorah. Fine. אימא מציעתא. Eima metzi'ata. Let's look at the middle
case. אני וחברתי טמאה. Ani vechaverti tme'ah. I and my friend are
טמאה. tme'ah. נאמנת על עצמה ואינה נאמנת על חברתה. Ne'emanet al atzmah
ve'einah ne'emanet al chavertah. Okay, she's believed about herself. You want to
say you're טמאה, tme'ah, גזונטערהייט. gezunterheit. But you're not believed about your
friend. ואי דאיכא עדים. Ve'ei de'ika edim. And if there are witnesses,
אמאי לא מהימנא? amai lo meheimna? If there are witnesses that you
were already taken captive, why aren't you believed about your friend? Your
friend is going to be presumed to be raped. So why shouldn't
you believe? Why does it say אינה נאמנת על חברתה, einah ne'emanet
al chavertah, which sounds like your friend is okay? She's not okay,
there are witnesses! אלא
פשיטא Ela pshita דליכא עדים. delika edim. It must be that there
are no witnesses. And therefore there are no witnesses, you don't make
your friend forbidden. You want to say you yourself are forbidden? גזונטערהייט.
gezunterheit. עם הסיפא, im ha-seifa, let's look at the end. אני וחברתי
טהורה. Ani v'chaverti tehorah. I and my friend are pure. נאמנת על
חברתה ואינה נאמנת על עצמה. Ne'emenet al chavertah v'eina ne'emenet al atzmah.
She's believed on her friend, not on herself. מדליכא עדים, Mi d'leika
edim, if there's no witnesses, עצמה מאי לא מהימנא, atzmah mai lo
ne'emnah, why isn't she believed about herself? If because basically she's the
one that's saying it all, she should be believed. אלא פשיטא דאיכא
עדים, Ela pshita d'ika edim, it must be that there are witnesses.
רישא וסיפא דאיכא עדים מציעתא דליכא עדים? Reisha v'seifa d'ika edim, metzi'asa
d'leika edim? How does this make sense? The beginning and the end
of this ברייתא braisa there are witnesses and the middle there are
not? So you're probably already lost, it's okay, I was lost too
when I was working through this, but basically it's just making problems
for itself because it's assuming that when it says that when she
says her friend is טמאה tmei'ah she's אינה נאמנת, eina ne'emenet, means
that her friend is presumed to be טהורה. tehorah. It could just
be אינה נאמנת, eina ne'emenet, which means that it doesn't make her
friend any more forbidden, it doesn't add any additional weight. But since
it did say in the middle case that when she says her
friend is טמאה tmei'ah she's not believed, and we're going to assume
to mean that the friend is assumed to be okay, the only
way the friend would be assumed to be okay would be if
there weren't witnesses. So how could there be that in the all
the other cases, presumably the reason she's not believed is because there
are witnesses? And in the middle case, we're assuming the friend is
okay without her, and she said the friend is טמאה tmei'ah and
we're saying the friend is still okay? Presumably that has to be
a case where there are no witnesses. So how do you make
sense out of all of this? So the גמרא Gemara says, so
אלא פשיטא רישא וסיפא דאיכא עדים, ela pshita reisha v'seifa d'ika edim,
the beginning and end there are witnesses and therefore in those cases
she's not believed to say she herself is טהורה, tehorah, but מציעתא
דליכא עדים, metzi'asa d'leika edim, and in the middle there are no
witnesses or else how do you explain why the friend is טהורה
tehorah when she says the friend is טמא? tamei? It must be
there are no witnesses in the middle. So אמר אביי, amar Abaye,
so אמר אביי אין, amar Abaye in, yeah, רישא וסיפא דאיכא עדים
מציעתא דליכא עדים, reisha v'seifa d'ika edim metzi'asa d'leika edim, yeah, that's
it, it's a weird case in the ברייתא, braisa, but the middle
case where the friend is presumed טהורה tehorah even when she testifies
טמאה tmei'ah is a case where there are no witnesses. All right
fine, that's what אביי Abaye says. רב פפא אמר, Rav Pappa amar,
רב פפא Rav Pappa says, כולה דאיכא עדים, kula d'ika edim, the
whole case is that there are witnesses, which is obviously the פשט.
pshat. But he's going to add another factor that's going to complicate
it even some more. ואיכא עד אחד דאפיך, v'ika ed echad d'apich,
if there's another עד אחד ed echad that actually is contradicting everything
this woman is saying. So let's take a case, talk about adding
something that is not in the text. Okay, so here's the case.
ואיכא עד אחד דאפיך. v'ika ed echad d'apich.
אמרה אני טמאה וחברתי טהורה. Amra Ani tmei'ah v'chaverti tehorah. She says
I'm טמאה tmei'ah and my friend is טהורה. tehorah. Okay, so and
again there are עדים edim that they were taken captive, she says
she's טמאה, tmei'ah, wonderful, her friend is טהורה, tehorah, she's believed. Okay,
ואמר לה עד אחד, v'amar lah ed echad, and another witness says,
את טהורה וחברתך טמאה, at tehorah v'chavertach tmei'ah, no, it's the opposite,
you're טהורה tehorah and your friend is
טמאה. tmei'ah. So now it's her against the עד ed whether what
her status is. She says she's טמאה, tmei'ah, the עד ed says
she's טהורה. tehorah. So in that case איהי שוויא לנפשה חתיכא דאיסורא.
ihi shavi l'nafshah chaticha d'issura. So she, she wants to make herself
forbidden, she can make herself forbidden even when a witness says that
she's טהורה. tehorah. Now how about by the friend? By the friend
she says טהורה tehorah and the עד ed says
טמאה. tmei'ah. וחברתי
טמאה... v'chaverti tmei'ah... okay,
וחברתה משתריא אפומא דדידה, v'chavertah mishtraya apumah d'didah, her friend is permitted
by her words. Now which is by the way shocking. Why is
it shocking? Because now we're finding out that not only is an
עד אחד ed echad and a woman believed to say that somebody
was not raped, she's even believed against direct testimony to the opposite.
Okay? Right? As long as there aren't two עדים, edim, she's saying
my friend wasn't raped and an עד אחד ed echad says your
friend was raped, we actually believe the woman that the friend wasn't
raped, even though it's established that they've been taken captive and there's
a specific עד אחד ed echad that she was raped, we believe
the testimony that she wasn't raped. So that's a huge חידוש chiddush
that we had not known until now. Okay that's point number one.
אני טהורה וחברתי טמאה. Ani tehorah v'chaverti tmei'ah. That's its reverse, I'm
טהורה tehorah and my friend is טמאה. tmei'ah. ואמר עד אחד, v'amar
ed echad, and the witness says to her no, את טמאה וחברתך
טהורה, at tmei'ah v'chavertach tehorah, it's the opposite, you're טמאה tmei'ah and
your friend is טהורה. tehorah.
איהי כיון דאיכא עדים לאו כל כמינה. ihi keivan d'ika edim lav
kol keminah. She, since there's witnesses she's not believed to say that
she's טהורה, tehorah, even forget the one witness that explicitly says she
was raped, there's witnesses that she was captured. וחברתה, v'chavertah, but her
friend, משתריא אפומא דעד, mishtraya apumah d'ed, and but here's the same
thing in reverse, but by the friend, even though she says the
friend is טמאה, tmei'ah, the one witness says the friend is טהורה,
tehorah, and therefore we always believe the witness that's saying טהורה tehorah
over the witness that says טמאה. tmei'ah. Right? Again, this is a
huge חידוש chiddush we hadn't learned until now. Right? You guys remember
the whole case about the husband dying? We had this just a
day or two ago, that one witness says the husband died and
one says he doesn't die, that the one we believe is the
one says he died, right? We give the one who says died
the weight of two witnesses. Now we're saying the same thing about
a case of a woman taken captive. One witness says raped, one
witness says not raped, doesn't matter who's the man, who's the woman
or whatever, we always believe the one who says not raped. Okay
so that's the big חידוש. chiddush. So the friend is טהורה tehorah
because even though she says the friend is טמאה, tmei'ah, the witness
says the friend is טהורה, tehorah, we always believe the one who
says that the friend is טהורה. tehorah. Okay?
Not about herself, right, but about somebody else.
We always believe the one... determine or whatever, we always believe the
one who says not raped. Okay, so that's the big חידוש. Chiddush.
So the friend is טהור Tahor because even though she says the
friend is טמא, Tamei, the witness says the friend is טהור. Tahor.
We always believe the one that says טהור Tahor if you're testifying
about someone else. So, פונדיתא, Pundita, אני וחברתי טמאה, ani ve-chaverti temei'ah,
אמר לה אחד, amar lei achad, לאו כל כמינך, lav kol keminnach,
חברתי משתעיא, chaverti mistaiya, פונדיתא. Pundita. Okay, אני וחברתי טמאה, ani ve-chaverti
temei'ah, I and my friend have both been raped, ואמר לה עד
אחד, ve-amar lah ed echad, no, את וחברתך טהורות, at ve-chavertach tehorot,
neither of you have been raped. היא, Hi, so for her own
status, שוויא לנפשה חתיכה דאיסורא, shavya l'nafshah chaticha d'issura,
she's always believed about herself to make herself forbidden. חברתה, Chaverta, her
friend, משתעיא אפומא דעד, mistaiya apuma d'ed,
against, she says the friend was raped, the עד אחד ed echad
says not, we believe the one that says not raped.
If it'd be presumed עדים edim then she wouldn't
be believed either, right?
Okay, so either way it makes
a difference
that עד, ed, right?
No, she says she's believed about her friend anyway.
Yeah, but but there's עדים edim that they were captive, so the
friend would be presumed to be raped. Okay, so המד"א? Ha Ma
Da? No, the Gemara says הא תו למה לי, ha tu lama
li, היינו רישא, hainu reisha, so why do you need the second
case? We've already said that, that you believe the עד אחד, ed
echad, you believe whichever one is saying the person wasn't raped. So,
מהו דתימא, ma d'teima, הני פרוותא וטהורות נינהו? hani parvata v'tehorot ninhu?
No,
maybe in this case that really, she herself, she shouldn't actually even
make herself forbidden. Why? And there would be, they really, because the
עד אחד ed echad says they're both טהור. Tahor. Maybe we should
believe the עד אחד ed echad even about her, and even about
herself? Ah, she's saying she herself is אסור, assur, shouldn't she, you
know, a person is believed against themselves? No, maybe she's saying she's
אסור assur for a different reason. והאי דקאמרה הכי, v'hai d'kamra hachi,
why is she saying that they've both been raped? תמות נפשי עם
פלשתים היא דקעבדא, tamus nafshi im pelishtim hi d'ka'avda, you remember that?
That it was willing to cause, you know, bad things to happen
to themselves as they can bring somebody else down with them that
they maybe don't like. So maybe in this case, she says 'me
and my friend are טמא', tamei maybe she's just trying to really
hurt her friend,
and nothing happened, because the עד אחד ed echad said both of
them were not raped. So therefore, and we can interpret what happened
as, okay, we believe the עד אחד ed echad because we normally
believe the person who says they're not raped, and therefore the fact
that she's saying both of them were raped is she's just trying
to bring her friend down. Okay? And therefore we shouldn't believe her
even against herself, and we shouldn't even say שוויא אנפשה. shavya anafshah.
קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, that no, if somebody says something
against themselves, they're bound by it even if there might be another
explanation.
Like the cases with, you know, the enmity, like the mother-in-law?
All right, so that fine, anyway, it's just as explaining what the
slight other חידוש Chiddush here.
Do you make a distinction and you believe for herself the שוויא
לנפשה shavya l'nafshah but not about the? Exactly.
Exactly, exactly. Okay, now, אני וחברתי טהורה, ani ve-chaverti tehorah, we're both
טהור, Tahor, ואמר לה עד אחד, ve-amar lah ed echad, את וחברתך
טמאה, at ve-chavertach temei'ah, you're both טמא. tamei. So again, when it's
about somebody else, we're always going to believe the one that says
טהור. Tahor. היא, Hi, about herself, כיון דאיכא עדים, keivan d'ika edim,
there're witnesses she was captive, and so and therefore, once there're witnesses
that she's captive and she's not believed for her own self to
make herself טהור, Tahor, לאו כל כמינה, lav kol keminnah, she's not
believed, and she remains presumed to be טמאה. temei'ah. חברתה משתעיא, chaverta
mistaiya, now the friend, she's saying טמאה temei'ah and the עד אחד
ed echad is saying
טהור, Tahor, I'm sorry, she's saying טהור Tahor and the עד ed
is saying טמא, tamei, excuse me, but we always go by the
one who says טהור. Tahor. חברתה משתעיא אפומא דידה. chaverta mistaiya apuma
didah. הא תו למה לי, ha tu lama li, why do you
need that, היינו רישא, hainu reisha, again isn't that the first case?
No, מהו דתימא, ma d'teima, אימת דאיכא הימנותא במקום דפסלה לנפשה, eimat
d'ika himanuta b'makom d'paslah l'nafshah, when is she believed about her friend,
if she's also if she's like making herself פסול passul in the
process, she's saying 'I'm טמא tamei and my friend is טהור'. Tahor
Since she's hurting herself, that gives believability to what she's saying about
the friend. אבל במקום דמכשרא לנפשה, aval b'makom d'machshra l'nafshah, she's saying
'we're both טהור', Tahor maybe she's just lying in order to get
them both off the hook? So אימא לא מהימנא, eima lo meheimna,
קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that she would. So although this
is a obviously a very twist, you know, forced read of the
ברייתא, Braita, we have now found out a huge חידוש Chiddush that
we did not know in the משנה, Mishna, which is the משנה
Mishna just told us that an עד אחד ed echad who even
a woman is believed to say that somebody was not raped. What
we have just now been told is even if it's an עד
ed against an עד, ed, and one עד ed says rape, then
one עד ed says not rape, and there were witnesses that they
were taken captive, we're still going to always believe whichever voice is
telling us not raped if it's one against one. You know, two
against two we could worry about, that's another story, but one against
one, we're always going to believe the voice that says not raped.
Okay, we will end with this for now.